Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
Dukungan Admin Tonton di kissasia.cam atau kisskh.org
=Yummy Yummy Yummy=
=Enak Enak Enak=
=Episode 3=
=Episode 3=
But so many years have passed.
Namun, bertahun-tahun telah berlalu.
Your appearance has changed greatly.
Penampilanmu telah banyak berubah.
How did this family
Bagaimana keluarga ini
recognize you?
mengenali kamu?
For the next few days,
Untuk beberapa hari ke depan,
keep a close eye on them.
awasi mereka dengan saksama.
I'll also find an opportunity
Saya juga akan menemukan kesempatan
to probe their background.
untuk menyelidiki latar belakang mereka.
To let our ancestor's guard down,
Untuk menurunkan kewaspadaan leluhur kita,
and then find a way home
dan kemudian menemukan jalan pulang
from Yunshui Manor,
dari Yunshui Manor,
our whole family will pretend to be
seluruh keluarga kita akan berpura-pura menjadi
poor relatives who have climbed up
kerabat miskin yang telah memanjat
to the new nobility.
untuk kaum bangsawan baru.
Round 1.
Babak 1.
Jicai, Jicai.
Jicai, Jicai.
Jicai, come with me over there.
Jicai, ikut aku ke sana.
There's a restroom.
Ada toilet.
The privy.
Jamban.
I've never seen such a nice privy
Aku belum pernah melihat jamban sebagus ini
in my whole life.
sepanjang hidupku.
Are you crazy, Shen Gongcai?
Apakah kamu gila, Shen Gongcai?
You want me to go see a privy with you now?
Kau ingin aku pergi ke toilet bersamamu sekarang?
It'll surely impress you.
Itu pasti akan membuat Anda terkesan.
- I won't go. - Come here.
- Aku tidak akan pergi. - Kemarilah.
Look. As I told you, it's beautiful.
Lihat. Seperti yang sudah kubilang, ini indah.
You must've never seen anything like it.
Anda pasti belum pernah melihat yang seperti itu.
(Privy) Come on, look.
(Privy) Ayo, lihat.
- Right here. - So clean?
- Di sini. - Begitu bersih?
The toilet paper is even scented.
Bahkan tisu toiletnya pun beraroma.
Exactly.
Tepat.
Look at the bottom of the toilet.
Lihatlah bagian bawah toilet.
It's lined with a layer of fine powder.
Itu dilapisi dengan lapisan bubuk halus.
The attention to detail here.
Perhatian terhadap detail di sini.
It won't splash.
Tidak akan terciprat.
Feel it, feel it.
Rasakan, rasakan.
Join me.
Bergabunglah denganku.
This is better than modern facilities.
Ini lebih baik daripada fasilitas modern.
I'm sure I can sit here without getting numb
Aku yakin aku bisa duduk di sini tanpa merasa mati rasa
in my legs.
di kakiku.
They've never even used a good toilet.
Mereka bahkan tidak pernah menggunakan toilet yang bagus.
- This courtyard is huge. - Round 2.
- Halaman ini luas sekali. - Ronde 2.
How much must this have cost?
Berapa biaya yang harus dikeluarkan untuk ini?
As expected of the Vice Prefect.
Seperti yang diharapkan dari Wakil Kepala Sekolah.
Yes.
Ya.
There's even a waterside pavilion.
Bahkan ada paviliun di tepi air.
This is much better than our house
Ini jauh lebih baik dari rumah kita
in the countryside.
di pedesaan.
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
Great.
Besar.
We've been pretending to be poor
Kita berpura-pura miskin
for three rounds now.
selama tiga putaran sekarang.
My legs are sore.
Kakiku sakit.
You just need more exercise.
Anda hanya perlu lebih banyak berolahraga.
Shall we put on a show of being a close-knit family?
Haruskah kita bersikap seperti keluarga yang akrab?
Just like this.
Seperti ini saja.
Enough.
Cukup.
Why push me?
Mengapa mendorongku?
Be quiet. They are watching.
Diamlah. Mereka sedang memperhatikan.
We want them to see.
Kami ingin mereka melihat.
We just want them to see.
Kami hanya ingin mereka melihat.
Look at you.
Lihatlah dirimu.
Be gentle; it hurts.
Bersikaplah lembut; itu menyakitkan.
Round 3.
Babak 3.
Dad,
Ayah,
Auntie said this tooth powder
Bibi bilang ini bubuk gigi
has ginger and astragalus in it.
mengandung jahe dan astragalus.
It's for protecting the teeth.
Itu untuk melindungi gigi.
It's true.
Itu benar.
Yangyang, the bristles of the toothbrush
Yangyang, bulu sikat gigi
seem to be made of horsehair.
tampaknya terbuat dari bulu kuda.
Didn't that performer at the inn say
Bukankah pemain di penginapan itu berkata
that only instruments use horsehair?
bahwa hanya instrumen yang menggunakan bulu kuda?
It's all because we were
Itu semua karena kita
too poor before.
terlalu miskin sebelumnya.
With this, I can eat as much candy as I want.
Dengan ini, saya bisa makan permen sebanyak yang saya mau.
I'm going to brush three times.
Saya akan menyikat gigi tiga kali.
That's too unambitious.
Itu terlalu tidak ambisius.
At least five times.
Setidaknya lima kali.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
The Vice Prefect is here.
Wakil Kepala Sekolah ada di sini.
Get up.
Bangun.
- Vice Prefect.
- Wakil Kepala Sekolah.
We've been here for a while.
Kami sudah ada di sini cukup lama.
Isn't the chef here slow?
Bukankah koki di sini lambat?
The main dishes still haven't been served.
Hidangan utama masih belum disajikan.
They've all been served.
Semuanya sudah dilayani.
Here's the thing.
Begini masalahnya.
Our young master
Tuan muda kita
never likes to fuss over food.
tidak pernah suka repot soal makanan.
If you're not used to it,
Jika Anda tidak terbiasa dengan hal itu,
you can
kamu bisa
leave on your own.
pergilah sendiri.
- No. - Liu Chang.
- Tidak. - Liu Chang.
Be polite.
Bersikaplah sopan.
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
Actually, we're indeed disturbing you.
Sebenarnya kami memang mengganggu Anda.
- It's fine. - Yes.
- Tidak apa-apa. - Ya.
The guest follows the host's lead.
Tamu mengikuti arahan tuan rumah.
The guest follows the host's lead?
Tamu mengikuti arahan tuan rumah?
Uncle, you're really easygoing.
Paman, Anda sungguh santai.
For example,
Misalnya,
I haven't greeted you today.
Aku belum menyapamu hari ini.
Usually, elders
Biasanya, orang tua
would've sent someone to ask.
akan mengirim seseorang untuk bertanya.
No, no.
Tidak, tidak.
Greet?
Menyapa?
I'll make up for my lack of manners now.
Aku akan menebus kurangnya sopan santunku sekarang.
Greetings, Uncle, Auntie.
Salam, Paman, Bibi.
I respectfully invite you
Saya dengan hormat mengundang Anda
to have a meal.
untuk makan.
- Don't. - Don't do this.
- Jangan. - Jangan lakukan ini.
Vice Prefect, don't.
Vice Prefect, don't.
Don't, don't.
Jangan, jangan.
Not again.
Not again.
Vice Prefect,
Wakil Prefek,
you can't do this.
you can't do this.
It's not appropriate.
It's not appropriate.
Uncle, Auntie, this is inappropriate.
Uncle, Auntie, this is inappropriate.
No, it's okay.
No, it's okay.
No, Vice Prefect.
No, Vice Prefect.
We must do this;
We must do this;
otherwise,
otherwise,
we'd be losing years of life.
we'd be losing years of life.
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
It's not appropriate.
It's not appropriate.
Uncle, Auntie, what are you thinking?
Uncle, Auntie, what are you thinking?
How can you bow
How can you bow
to a junior like me?
to a junior like me?
Well...
Dengan baik...
Please understand.
Please understand.
My parents can't bear
My parents can't bear
a dignified Vice Prefect
a dignified Vice Prefect
bowing to them.
bowing to them.
We're all commoners,
We're all commoners,
living here for free.
living here for free.
How could we possibly accept your bow?
How could we possibly accept your bow?
- Yes. - That's right.
- Yes. - That's right.
If anyone should bow,
If anyone should bow,
it should be us bowing to you.
it should be us bowing to you.
Yes.
Ya.
We're at home.
We're at home.
I'm just a junior,
I'm just a junior,
not the Vice Prefect.
not the Vice Prefect.
There's no need to be so formal with me.
There's no need to be so formal with me.
Vice Prefect, that'll be great.
Vice Prefect, that'll be great.
From now on,
Mulai sekarang,
let's not worry about these formalities.
let's not worry about these formalities.
Let's eat.
Ayo makan.
Eat.
Makan.
Vice Prefect, sit.
Vice Prefect, sit.
Have a seat, Vice Prefect.
Have a seat, Vice Prefect.
Vice Prefect, don't mind us.
Vice Prefect, don't mind us.
We're used to being casual in the countryside.
We're used to being casual in the countryside.
We're not very proper when we eat.
We're not very proper when we eat.
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
After we were engaged,
After we were engaged,
it seems there was no contact.
it seems there was no contact.
(Probing us again.)
(Probing us again.)
(Grandpa didn't tell me)
(Grandpa didn't tell me)
(everything about the Cuis.)
(everything about the Cuis.)
(Our ancestor doesn't have much of an accent.)
(Our ancestor doesn't have much of an accent.)
(He must've come to Yong'an)
(He must've come to Yong'an)
(when he was very young.)
(when he was very young.)
Your family later moved to the Capital.
Your family later moved to the Capital.
Naturally, your contact with us decreased.
Naturally, your contact with us decreased.
Lady Shen, do you know
Lady Shen, do you know
what happened to my family
what happened to my family
after they moved to the Capital?
after they moved to the Capital?
We knew we were humble
We knew we were humble
and not a match for your family.
and not a match for your family.
We thought that in a few years,
We thought that in a few years,
the engagement would be called off,
the engagement would be called off,
so we didn't want to disturb.
so we didn't want to disturb.
Later,
Nanti,
we heard that your family had trouble,
we heard that your family had trouble,
but we didn't dare to ask for details.
but we didn't dare to ask for details.
If not for the current difficulties,
If not for the current difficulties,
we wouldn't have come to trouble you.
we wouldn't have come to trouble you.
So,
Jadi,
after my family moved here,
after my family moved here,
you lost contact with them,
you lost contact with them,
and you knew nothing about them?
and you knew nothing about them?
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
Now that I've changed my name,
Now that I've changed my name,
how did you all
how did you all
find me?
find me?
Have you forgotten?
Have you forgotten?
That day,
That day,
when you took office and inspected Juxian Alley,
when you took office and inspected Juxian Alley,
we happened to be selling pancakes,
we happened to be selling pancakes,
and we recognized you.
and we recognized you.
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
So many years apart didn't change
So many years apart didn't change
the fact that we're in-laws.
the fact that we're in-laws.
I took a look and knew you were my future son-in-law.
I took a look and knew you were my future son-in-law.
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
I also recognized you.
I also recognized you.
I was too excited.
I was too excited.
I lost my composure.
I lost my composure.
I have to go to court.
I have to go to court.
Take your time.
Take your time.
Vice Prefect, goodbye.
Vice Prefect, goodbye.
Goodbye, Vice Prefect.
Goodbye, Vice Prefect.
Dad, why haven't you stood up?
Dad, why haven't you stood up?
My legs are numb.
My legs are numb.
I can't move.
I can't move.
(Clear and Bright)
(Clear and Bright)
(Ancestor's Room)
(Ancestor's Room)
(Mom, Dad, Yangyang)
(Mom, Dad, Yangyang)
Everyone, well done.
Everyone, well done.
You got up early,
You got up early,
pretending to be inexperienced,
pretending to be inexperienced,
wandering around,
wandering around,
but actually surveying
but actually surveying
the terrain of Yunshui Manor.
the terrain of Yunshui Manor.
The covert operation was
The covert operation was
very successful.
very successful.
I really think that privy is nice.
I really think that privy is nice.
We need to maintain a style of bold analysis
We need to maintain a style of bold analysis
and careful verification,
and careful verification,
trying to find a way back to the modern era
trying to find a way back to the modern era
(Water Pavilion) in Yunshui Manor.
(Water Pavilion) in Yunshui Manor.
Well said.
Benar sekali.
Next,
Berikutnya,
I'll also give a constructive speech.
Saya juga akan memberikan pidato yang membangun.
To get to the bottom
Untuk sampai ke dasar
of the truth,
dari kebenaran,
we need first to review
kita perlu meninjau terlebih dahulu
what happened on the day we came here.
apa yang terjadi pada hari kami datang ke sini.
According to Jicai,
Menurut Jicai,
she was chasing a guy
dia sedang mengejar seorang pria
and walked into this corridor.
dan berjalan ke koridor ini.
After going through the corridor,
Setelah melewati koridor,
(Back Door) she came to the back door,
(Pintu Belakang) dia datang ke pintu belakang,
opened the back door,
membuka pintu belakang,
and came to this era.
dan datang ke era ini.
If we go back the same way,
Jika kita kembali dengan cara yang sama,
could we
bisakah kita
go back?
kembali?
- That makes sense.
- Itu masuk akal.
Help!
Membantu!
(Langhuan Chamber, Back Door)
(Ruang Langhuan, Pintu Belakang)
(Back Door)
(Pintu belakang)
The place we were together
Tempat kita bersama
before we came to this era was
sebelum kita sampai pada era ini adalah
the ancestral hall.
aula leluhur.
So, should we go back there?
Jadi, haruskah kita kembali ke sana?
We've been there.
Kami pernah mengalaminya.
The ancestral hall
Aula leluhur
(Langhuan Chamber) is now this small study.
(Kamar Langhuan) sekarang menjadi ruang belajar kecil ini.
Your dad and I
Ayahmu dan aku
have been around this area this morning.
telah berada di sekitar area ini pagi ini.
This place
Tempat ini
is well guarded.
dijaga dengan baik.
It's not easy
Itu tidak mudah
to get in.
untuk masuk.
So, what do we do now?
Jadi, apa yang kita lakukan sekarang?
Why is no one speaking?
Mengapa tak seorang pun berbicara?
Shen Jianshe, what's your name for?
Shen Jianshe, siapa namamu?
It's to give a constructive speech.
Itu untuk memberikan pidato yang membangun.
I think
Menurut saya
since the ancestral hall
sejak aula leluhur
is guarded,
dijaga,
if we all go there,
jika kita semua pergi ke sana,
it's easy to be discovered.
mudah untuk ditemukan.
If we could
Jika kita bisa
send just one person,
kirim satu orang saja,
the target would be smaller,
targetnya akan lebih kecil,
and we could likely break through the blockade.
dan kita mungkin bisa menerobos blokade.
What do you mean?
Apa maksudmu?
Me?
Aku?
No, no, no.
Tidak tidak tidak.
I can't, I can't.
Aku tak bisa, aku tak bisa.
I can't.
Aku tidak bisa.
I won't go.
Aku tidak akan pergi.
For fairness, how about we vote?
Demi keadilan, bagaimana kalau kita memilih?
Let's vote.
Mari kita memilih.
- Okay.
- Oke.
Mom, they're playing tricks.
Bu, mereka sedang bermain trik.
They're bribing and cheating.
Mereka menyuap dan menipu.
Raise your hands to vote for Shen Shaoguang.
Angkat tangan Anda untuk memilih Shen Shaoguang.
Yangyang.
Yangyang.
Look, three votes are for you.
Lihat, tiga suara untuk Anda.
It's me again?
Aku lagi?
Mom...
Mama...
Jicai,
Jicai,
it has to be you.
itu harus kamu.
In our family, you're the smartest
Di keluarga kami, kamu yang paling pintar
and the most quick-witted.
dan paling cerdas.
Look at your dad and your brother.
Lihatlah ayahmu dan saudaramu.
Who can you rely on?
Siapa yang dapat Anda andalkan?
- I... - Right?
- Aku... - Benar?
Jicai.
Jicai.
Fine.
Bagus.
Leave.
Meninggalkan.
- Yes.
- Ya.
Oh, no, Young Master,
Oh, tidak, Tuan Muda,
I just thought of something.
Aku baru saja memikirkan sesuatu.
The Shens
Keluarga Shen
recognized you by your appearance.
mengenali Anda dari penampilan Anda.
Doesn't that mean someone else
Bukankah itu berarti orang lain?
at the court might notice too?
di pengadilan mungkin memperhatikan juga?
After so long in the Capital,
Setelah sekian lama di Ibukota,
you finally thought of that.
Anda akhirnya memikirkan hal itu.
Don't worry about that.
Jangan khawatir tentang itu.
Since I'm back,
Karena aku sudah kembali,
I never intended to hide my identity forever.
Saya tidak pernah bermaksud menyembunyikan identitas saya selamanya.
I found in the documents
Saya menemukan di dokumen
that this secret code is the numbers used by Huoxun Kingdom,
bahwa kode rahasia ini adalah angka yang digunakan oleh Kerajaan Huoxun,
which correspond
yang sesuai
to 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9.
ke 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, dan 9.
These are numbers?
Ini angka?
These are notches.
Ini adalah takik.
If we match the correct numbers
Jika kita mencocokkan angka yang benar
to the notches, the lock will open.
pada takik tersebut, kunci akan terbuka.
Nine numbers.
Sembilan angka.
Eight holes.
Delapan lubang.
Altogether,
Sama sekali,
tens of millions of possibilities.
puluhan juta kemungkinan.
Tens of millions of possibilities?
Puluhan juta kemungkinan?
That means it's impossible to figure it out, right?
Itu berarti mustahil untuk mengetahuinya, bukan?
Young Master, this is too...
Tuan Muda, ini terlalu...
Quiet.
Diam.
Young Master,
Tuan Muda,
how about I do it?
Bagaimana kalau aku yang melakukannya?
Even if I don't eat or drink in this life,
Bahkan jika aku tidak makan atau minum dalam hidup ini,
don't get married or have children,
jangan menikah atau punya anak,
I will try all these possibilities
Saya akan mencoba semua kemungkinan ini
to repay you.
untuk membalas budi Anda.
Quiet.
Diam.
I remember now.
Sekarang saya ingat.
Your father once taught you
Ayahmu pernah mengajarimu
how to open a lock by sound.
cara membuka kunci dengan suara.
I can have a daughter then.
Kalau begitu, saya bisa punya anak perempuan.
I think what I need to learn is how to make a silencing potion.
Saya pikir yang perlu saya pelajari adalah cara membuat ramuan peredam suara.
One, two, three.
Satu dua tiga.
Four.
Empat.
Five.
Lima.
Two, two.
Dua, dua.
Three, four.
Tiga, empat.
Five.
Lima.
There's no one here.
Tidak ada siapa-siapa di sini.
So lucky.
Beruntung sekali.
Even the guards have left their posts?
Bahkan para penjaga telah meninggalkan pos mereka?
Someone's coming.
Seseorang datang.
The portrait of the ancestors
Potret para leluhur
used to be in here.
dulu ada di sini.
(No wonder dramas are always shot this way.)
(Tidak heran drama selalu direkam dengan cara ini.)
(So, ancient mechanisms are really like this.)
(Jadi, mekanisme kuno memang seperti ini.)
(No Visitors Allowed)
(Tidak Diperbolehkan Pengunjung)
(Private Area, Do Not Enter)
(Area Pribadi, Dilarang Masuk)
(This lock is...)
(Kunci ini...)
(It's here.)
(Itu dia.)
(Could it be that the time-space tunnel)
(Mungkinkah terowongan ruang-waktu)
(that can send us back is inside?)
(yang bisa mengirim kita kembali ada di dalam?)
Eight, eight, eight.
Delapan, delapan, delapan.
Eight.
Delapan.
Eight, eight.
Delapan, delapan.
She opened the lock
Dia membuka kuncinya
so easily?
dengan begitu mudahnya?
(Why haven't I gone back?)
(Mengapa saya belum kembali?)
(But this is exactly the lock.)
(Tetapi inilah kuncinya.)
(It came with us.)
(Itu datang bersama kami.)
(I should be right.)
(Saya seharusnya benar.)
(This house)
(Rumah ini)
(is the time-space tunnel connecting)
(adalah terowongan ruang-waktu yang menghubungkan)
(the past and the future.)
(masa lalu dan masa depan)
(We can definitely go home through here.)
(Kita pasti bisa pulang lewat sini.)
Vice Prefect.
Wakil Prefek.
What are you doing?
Apa yang sedang kamu lakukan?
I...
SAYA...
I accidentally got lost,
Aku tidak sengaja tersesat,
accidentally walked into the study,
secara tidak sengaja masuk ke ruang belajar,
accidentally came to this room,
secara tidak sengaja datang ke ruangan ini,
accidentally opened the lock,
tidak sengaja membuka kunci,
and came in.
dan masuk.
Accidentally?
Secara tidak sengaja?
This lock has numbers from Huoxun Kingdom.
Kunci ini memiliki nomor dari Kerajaan Huoxun.
Ordinary people don't recognize them at all.
Orang awam tidak mengenali mereka sama sekali.
Yet you opened it.
Namun Anda membukanya.
How could you have done it accidentally?
Bagaimana Anda bisa melakukannya secara tidak sengaja?
I don't know the Huoxun Kingdom
Aku tidak tahu Kerajaan Huoxun
you're talking about,
kamu sedang berbicara tentang,
but I do recognize these numbers.
tetapi saya mengenali angka-angka ini.
We used to be in business,
Kami dulu berbisnis,
running a diner.
menjalankan restoran.
We don't know much,
Kami tidak tahu banyak,
but we're familiar with numbers. Look.
tapi kita akrab dengan angka. Lihat.
Eight, eight, eight, eight, eight, eight, eight, eight.
Delapan, delapan, delapan, delapan, delapan, delapan, delapan, delapan.
It implies great wealth.
Itu menyiratkan kekayaan besar.
It means prosperity and making money.
Artinya kemakmuran dan menghasilkan uang.
That's too easy to guess
Itu terlalu mudah untuk ditebak
for people in business.
untuk orang-orang yang berkecimpung di dunia bisnis.
(Tai Xuan Jing)
(Tai Xuan Jing)
Young Master,
Tuan Muda,
she just got away...?
dia baru saja lolos...?
She won't.
Dia tidak akan melakukannya.
Without the cooperation of many parties,
Tanpa adanya kerjasama dari banyak pihak,
it would've been impossible
itu tidak mungkin
to frame my father without any flaws.
untuk menjebak ayahku tanpa cacat apa pun.
My family was exterminated.
Keluargaku dibasmi.
How could the Shens, related to us by engagement,
Bagaimana mungkin Shens, yang memiliki hubungan dengan kita melalui pertunangan,
have been spared?
telah terhindar?
Could it be
Mungkinkah itu?
that they were just impostors all along?
bahwa mereka hanyalah penipu selama ini?
And you were engaged
Dan kamu sudah bertunangan
to someone else?
ke orang lain?
Or perhaps
Atau mungkin
she's indeed my fiancée,
dia memang tunanganku,
but they sought protection
tapi mereka mencari perlindungan
and pledged allegiance to someone.
dan berjanji setia kepada seseorang.
They're likely spies.
Mereka mungkin mata-mata.
That would explain
Itu akan menjelaskan
why this woman knows
mengapa wanita ini tahu
Huoxun Kingdom's numbers.
Angka-angka Kerajaan Huoxun.
I don't even know them.
Saya bahkan tidak mengenal mereka.
They might have been trained in the Western Regions.
Mereka mungkin telah dilatih di Wilayah Barat.
What should we do next?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan selanjutnya?
Should we bring them back
Haruskah kita membawa mereka kembali?
and torture them for info?
dan menyiksa mereka untuk mendapatkan informasi?
The lock on the Langhuan Chamber door
Kunci di pintu Kamar Langhuan
is confirmed to be the same lock as the one from the back door
dipastikan kuncinya sama dengan yang ada di pintu belakang
of Yunshui Manor when we came to this era.
dari Yunshui Manor saat kita memasuki era ini.
Good.
Bagus.
That's settled then.
Itu sudah diputuskan.
Since modern items have appeared,
Sejak munculnya benda-benda modern,
Yunshui Manor must definitely be
Yunshui Manor pastinya harus
a time-space tunnel.
terowongan ruang-waktu.
Absolutely.
Sangat.
But now, Vice Prefect Lin
Tapi sekarang, Wakil Prefek Lin
is already suspicious of us.
sudah curiga pada kita.
I think this is a bit troublesome.
Menurutku ini agak merepotkan.
But he's an official.
Tapi dia seorang pejabat.
He probably can't
Dia mungkin tidak bisa
lay a hand on us directly.
memukul kami secara langsung.
We still have some time.
Kita masih punya waktu.
That makes sense.
Itu masuk akal.
Before our ancestor reacts,
Sebelum nenek moyang kita bereaksi,
let's make a quick getaway.
ayo kita pergi sebentar.
I think we should do this:
Saya pikir kita harus melakukan ini:
Let's recall the details
Mari kita mengingat kembali detailnya
of that day again.
hari itu lagi.
What else happened
Apa lagi yang terjadi
when we went to Yunshui Manor?
ketika kita pergi ke Yunshui Manor?
For example, what we touched
Misalnya saja apa yang kita sentuh
and what we said.
dan apa yang kami katakan.
We can't overlook any detail.
Kita tidak dapat mengabaikan detail apa pun.
Maybe
Mungkin
if we recreate
jika kita menciptakan kembali
the situation of that day,
situasi pada hari itu,
it might work.
itu mungkin berhasil.
Grandma,
Nenek,
when I time-traveled,
ketika saya melakukan perjalanan waktu,
I didn't do my homework.
Aku tidak mengerjakan pekerjaan rumahku.
Does that mean if I never do my homework,
Apakah itu berarti jika aku tidak pernah mengerjakan pekerjaan rumahku,
I can time-travel back?
Bisakah saya melakukan perjalanan waktu kembali?
You...
Anda...
You just don't want to do your homework,
Kamu hanya tidak ingin mengerjakan pekerjaan rumahmu,
right?
Kanan?
Liu Chang.
Liu Chang.
In the spring of Tianxing Year 22,
Pada musim semi tahun Tianxing 22,
I met Fifth Master Xiao.
Saya bertemu Guru Kelima Xiao.
He always carried writing paper with him,
Dia selalu membawa kertas tulis bersamanya,
and I followed his example and wrote this note.
dan saya mengikuti teladannya dan menulis catatan ini.
This is Father's note.
Ini catatan Ayah.
Right, Gongcai.
Benar, Gongcai.
When you time-traveled that day,
Ketika kamu melakukan perjalanan waktu pada hari itu,
I remember you were wearing thong sandals,
Aku ingat kamu memakai sandal jepit,
and you hadn't cut your toenails.
dan kamu belum memotong kuku kakimu.
But when you tried to time-travel that day,
Tapi ketika Anda mencoba melakukan perjalanan waktu pada hari itu,
you weren't wearing thong sandals,
kamu tidak memakai sandal jepit,
and you still hadn't cut your toenails.
dan kamu masih belum memotong kuku kakimu.
Come on, Dad.
Ayo, Ayah.
Does that have anything to do with it?
Apakah itu ada hubungannya dengan itu?
Thong sandals, toenails?
Sandal jepit, kuku kaki?
Do they have that much energy
Apakah mereka punya energi sebanyak itu?
to affect time-travel?
mempengaruhi perjalanan waktu?
I'll think about it again.
Saya akan memikirkannya lagi.
I'll look for reasons
Aku akan mencari alasan
from myself.
dari diriku sendiri.
What are you doing?
Apa yang sedang kamu lakukan?
I remember.
Saya ingat.
Weren't we in the ancestral hall at that time?
Bukankah saat itu kita sedang berada di balai leluhur?
Didn't we all worship
Bukankah kita semua menyembah?
the portrait of our ancestors,
potret nenek moyang kita,
hoping for their blessings?
berharap restu mereka?
Yes, yes.
Ya, ya.
Maybe this time,
Mungkin kali ini,
if we worship
jika kita beribadah
the real person,
orang yang sebenarnya,
we can go back.
kita bisa kembali.
Wait.
Tunggu.
I think he has a point.
Menurutku, dia ada benarnya.
If we can
Jika kita bisa
worship the real person
menyembah orang yang nyata
and make this event
dan buat acara ini
more grand and solemn,
lebih megah dan khidmat,
we will definitely be able
kita pasti bisa
to time-travel back.
untuk melakukan perjalanan waktu kembali.
That makes sense.
Itu masuk akal.
In Tianxing Year 23,
Pada Tahun Tianxing 23,
Che
Itu
grew a bit taller.
tumbuh sedikit lebih tinggi.
Tianxing Year 26...
Tianxing Tahun 26...
It was the year Father was framed.
Tahun itu Ayah dijebak.
(How could he become the Vice Minister of War?)
(Bagaimana dia bisa menjadi Wakil Menteri Perang?)
He discovered on March 26
Dia menemukannya pada tanggal 26 Maret
that someone was selling official positions,
bahwa seseorang menjual jabatan resmi,
and their hands had even reached the Ministry of War.
dan tangan mereka bahkan telah mencapai Kementerian Perang.
Father found out that someone
Ayah menemukan seseorang
was manipulating the appointments,
memanipulasi penunjukan,
which is why he sent Mother and me
itulah sebabnya dia mengirim Ibu dan aku
back to our hometown in Qingyang in May.
kembali ke kampung halaman kami di Qingyang pada bulan Mei.
He sensed
Dia merasakan
that something would happen to him,
bahwa sesuatu akan terjadi padanya,
thinking that he could protect the family this way.
berpikir bahwa dia bisa melindungi keluarga dengan cara ini.
But the mastermind behind it all
Tapi dalang di balik semua ini
pinned everything on him.
melimpahkan segala sesuatu padanya.
Father
Ayah
died in prison,
meninggal di penjara,
my family was exterminated,
keluargaku dibasmi,
and our property was confiscated.
dan harta benda kami disita.
This note is useless,
Catatan ini tidak berguna,
even if it's presented in court.
bahkan jika itu disampaikan di pengadilan.
To overturn the case,
Untuk membatalkan kasus tersebut,
we must find more evidence.
kita harus menemukan lebih banyak bukti.
(It seems we haven't gone back.)
(Sepertinya kita belum kembali.)
(What's going on?)
(Apa yang sedang terjadi?)
(Did we go back?)
(Apakah kita kembali?)
(I don't know.)
(Aku tidak tahu.)
Jicai.
Jicai.
- Do you think...? - What are you doing?
- Menurutmu...? - Apa yang sedang kamu lakukan?
Don't be afraid.
Jangan takut.
Don't be afraid, Yangyang.
Jangan takut, Yangyang.
Lady Shen, please.
Nyonya Shen, silakan.
Vice Prefect.
Wakil Prefek.
What happened last night was a misunderstanding.
Apa yang terjadi tadi malam adalah kesalahpahaman.
I can explain.
Saya bisa menjelaskannya.
Last night,
Tadi malam,
your whole family sneaked into my room,
seluruh keluargamu menyelinap ke kamarku,
intending to harm me.
bermaksud menyakitiku.
No, absolutely not.
Tidak, sama sekali tidak.
You've misunderstood.
Anda salah paham.
Misunderstood?
Disalahpahami?
We sneaked into your room
Kami menyelinap ke kamarmu
to pray for your blessings.
untuk berdoa memohon berkat Anda.
Pray?
Berdoa?
Our grandfather once told us a method:
Kakek kami pernah memberi tahu kami sebuah metode:
If we wash our hands, burn incense,
Jika kita mencuci tangan, membakar dupa,
offer holy items,
mempersembahkan barang-barang suci,
scatter flower petals,
taburkan kelopak bunga,
and bow three times to the person
dan membungkuk tiga kali kepada orang tersebut
we deeply admire,
kami sangat mengagumi,
we can pray for their blessings.
kita dapat berdoa memohon berkat mereka.
We've been living at your house for free,
Kami tinggal di rumahmu secara gratis,
and we feel really bad about it,
dan kami merasa sangat buruk tentang hal itu,
so we held this ceremony
jadi kami mengadakan upacara ini
to pray
untuk berdoa
for your good fortune and long life.
untuk keberuntungan dan umur panjang Anda.
Actually,
Sebenarnya,
Lady Shen,
Nyonya Shen,
you are not the lady
kamu bukan wanita itu
who was engaged to me,
yang bertunangan denganku,
are you?
apakah kamu?
That secret code lock
Kunci kode rahasia itu
can't be solved
tidak bisa diselesaikan
just by guessing.
hanya dengan menebak.
How could you know
Bagaimana kamu bisa tahu?
what the code is?
apa kodenya?
Why don't you be more honest?
Mengapa kamu tidak lebih jujur?
What are you really after?
Apa sebenarnya yang Anda cari?
Tell me.
Beri tahu saya.
Maybe I can help you.
Mungkin saya bisa membantu Anda.
Do you have to bully me like this?
Apakah kamu harus menggertakku seperti ini?
I...
SAYA...
In the old days in Qingyang,
Di masa lalu di Qingyang,
you used to be so upright
kamu dulu sangat tegak
and righteous.
dan benar.
We think you'd never turn a blind eye to friends in trouble.
Kami pikir Anda tidak akan pernah menutup mata terhadap teman yang sedang dalam kesulitan.
I know it's not easy for you,
Aku tahu ini tidak mudah bagimu,
and we can't help you,
dan kami tidak dapat membantu Anda,
but we still hope for a bit of kindness.
tetapi kami masih berharap sedikit kebaikan.
Yet you want to deny my identity
Namun kamu ingin menyangkal identitasku
and completely shirk responsibility.
dan sepenuhnya mengabaikan tanggung jawab.
We just don't deserve it.
Kita tidak pantas mendapatkannya.
We will leave on our own.
Kami akan pergi sendiri.
I...
SAYA...
I didn't mean that.
Aku tidak bermaksud begitu.
You...
Anda...
Please don't cry.
Tolong jangan menangis.
(It seems shedding tears on the spot)
(Sepertinya meneteskan air mata di tempat)
(is also useful in ancient times.)
(juga berguna di zaman kuno.)
If you want me to leave,
Jika kamu ingin aku pergi,
I will definitely leave with my family.
Saya pasti akan pergi bersama keluarga saya.
Just say the word.
Katakan saja kata itu.
I didn't mean it that way.
Aku tidak bermaksud seperti itu.
It's just
Itu hanya
that I don't quite remember how it was
bahwa aku tidak begitu ingat bagaimana itu
with your family when I was a child,
dengan keluargamu saat aku masih kecil,
so I need to confirm with you.
Jadi saya perlu konfirmasi dengan Anda.
I understand.
Saya mengerti.
You've been through a lot.
Kamu telah melalui banyak hal.
It's hard to trust others.
Sulit untuk memercayai orang lain.
It's okay.
Tidak apa-apa.
If you have any questions,
Jika Anda memiliki pertanyaan,
just ask us.
tanyakan saja pada kami.
Time will tell.
Waktu yang akan menjawabnya.
You'll eventually know
Kamu akhirnya akan tahu
what kind of people we are.
orang macam apa kita.
I...
SAYA...
What are you going to say?
Apa yang akan kamu katakan?
You have a question so soon?
Anda punya pertanyaan secepatnya?
I was wondering
aku sedang bertanya-tanya
if you'd like
jika kamu mau
to have some tea.
untuk minum teh.
(Shaoguang's Food Notes)
(Catatan Makanan Shaoguang)
(Goose Cake, goose meat as dessert)
(Kue Angsa, daging angsa sebagai hidangan penutup)
(Guixiang Tavern; Sorry, goose. (Amazing!))
(Guixiang Tavern; Maaf, angsa. (Luar biasa!))
♪Wear a sunset glow upon the brow♪
???Mengenakan cahaya matahari terbenam di dahi???
♪Breeze sways, wind chimes hang below the cloud♪
???Angin bertiup, lonceng angin tergantung di bawah awan???
♪Hear one chime ring, tugging at the heart♪
???Mendengar bunyi lonceng yang berbunyi, menyentak hati???
♪True feelings perhaps can only be sensed♪
???Perasaan sebenarnya mungkin hanya bisa dirasakan???
♪Misty is you, clear is you♪
???Berkabut itu kamu, cerah itu kamu???
♪Seeking stars in fog, seeing your shadow under the moon♪
???Mencari bintang dalam kabut, melihat bayanganmu di bawah bulan???
♪Words held back, feelings unrestrained♪
???Kata-kata tertahan, perasaan tak terkendali???
♪Could the road ahead, let us gaze but not doubt♪
???Bisakah jalan di depan, mari kita tatap namun tak ragu???
♪Mistook all eyes see as cold ice♪
???Mengira semua mata melihat sebagai es dingin???
♪Yet let dusk dye the ears and temples red♪
???Namun biarkan senja mewarnai telinga dan pelipis menjadi merah???
♪Even holding breath couldn't help but stop♪
???Bahkan menahan napas pun tak kuasa menahannya???
♪Exposing my warmed heart held tight♪
???Menunjukkan hatiku yang hangat yang dipegang erat???
♪Bustling is you, desolate is you♪
???Sibukkah kamu, sepikah kamu???
♪Reservedly drawing you into this life♪
???Dengan sengaja menarikmu ke dalam kehidupan ini???
♪Hesitating, undecided, the heart hard to deceive♪
???Ragu-ragu, bimbang, hati sulit tertipu???
♪Worldly rules and taboos, how could they make me give up♪
???Aturan dan tabu duniawi, bagaimana mungkin itu membuatku menyerah???
♪When rushing to you, leaving my deep thoughts in disarray♪
???Saat bergegas menghampirimu, meninggalkan pikiran mendalamku berantakan???
♪I still foolishly see it as a good time♪
???Saya masih bodoh melihatnya sebagai saat yang baik???
♪Heart stirs, wind swirls the lightest ripples♪
???Jantung berdebar, angin menimbulkan riak-riak yang paling ringan???
♪A thousand tangled thoughts concealed♪
???Seribu pikiran kusut tersembunyi???
♪Saved a whole lifetime, hastening to you, urgent over miles♪
???Menyelamatkan seluruh hidup, bergegas ke tempatmu, mendesak sejauh bermil-mil???
♪To make the wandering heart return home henceforth♪
???Untuk membuat hati yang mengembara kembali pulang untuk selanjutnya???
♪To draw near what seems beyond reach♪
???Mendekati apa yang tampaknya di luar jangkauan???
♪Through life and death changes, only we never cease, never yield♪
???Melalui perubahan hidup dan mati, hanya kita yang tak pernah berhenti, tak pernah menyerah???
♪Perhaps affection barely passes muster♪
???Mungkin kasih sayang hampir tidak bisa diterima???
♪But love forever♪
???Tapi cinta selamanya???
♪Will make up for our mutual care, mutual bond♪
???Akan menebus kepedulian kita bersama, ikatan kita bersama???
♪Saved a whole lifetime, hastening to you, urgent over miles♪
???Menyelamatkan seluruh hidup, bergegas ke tempatmu, mendesak sejauh bermil-mil???
♪To make the wandering heart return home from now♪
???Untuk membuat hati yang mengembara kembali pulang mulai sekarang???
♪To dare approach what seems beyond reach♪
???Berani mendekati sesuatu yang tampaknya di luar jangkauan???
♪Through life and death changes♪
???Melalui perubahan hidup dan mati???
♪Only you, never cease, never yield♪
???Hanya kamu, yang tak pernah berhenti, yang tak pernah menyerah???